Guide to the Martin L. Friedland research materials for "The Death of Old Man Rice," 1900-1992 MS 444
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Martin L. Friedland research materials for "The Death of Old Man Rice"
1900-1992
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Friedland, Martin L.
MS 444
11 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
This collection documents Dr. Martin Friedland's research and writing of his book, "The Death of Old Man Rice" (published 1994), and includes rough working notes, manuscript drafts, subject files, and photocopies of the original trial manuscript.
Biographical Sketch
Martin L. Friedland, a highly respected University of Toronto law professor, is the author of numerous periodical articles and books, including "The Death of Old Man Rice", a work of legal history that chronicles the murder of William Marsh Rice, the trial and subsequent appeals. "The Death of Old Man Rice" was published by New York University Press, c. 1994.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents Dr. Friedland's research and writing of his book, "The Death of Old Man Rice", and includes rough working notes, manuscript drafts, subject files, and photocopies of the original trial manuscript.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. Martin L. Friedland, July 1995.
Related Material
See also Early Rice Institute papers. Finding aid to the collection available at http://library.rice.edu/collections/WRC/finding-aids/university-archives/early-rice-institute-papers/.
Index Terms
Subjects
Trials (Murder); Murder victims
Document Types
newspapers
Subjects (Persons)
Rice, William Marsh; Friedland, Martin L.
- Series I: Newspaper Photocopies, 1900-1940
  - New York Times, 1900-1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - New York Times, 1903-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New York Times, 1900-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - New York Times Index (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New York Times-Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - New York World, up to May 1902 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - New York Evening Journal (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New York American (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York Sun (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - New York Herald and New York Tribune (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Tulsa Daily World, 1912-1912; Tulsa Daily Democrat, 1912-1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - St. Louis Post Dispatch; St. Louis Globe Democrat; St. Louis Star (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Albany Times Union; Albany Evening Journal (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Denver Post; Colorado Springs Gazette (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Houston Post; Chicago Record Tribune (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II: Biographical Files
  - Biographical Files, Folder 1 of 6 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Biographical Files, Folder 2 of 6 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Biographical Files, Folder 3 of 6 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Biographical Files, Folder 4 of 6 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Biographical Files, Folder 5 of 6 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Biographical Files, Folder 6 of 6 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series III: Manuscript and Typescript drafts, notes, sources, 1991-1992
  - Draft of Manuscript, 1991-1992, Drafts 1-49 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Draft of Manuscript, Drafts 50-98 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Draft, August 1992, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Draft, August 1992, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Draft, March 1993, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Draft, March 1993, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Draft, May 1993, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Draft, May 1993, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Rough Working Notes, Sections 2-33 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Rough Working Notes, Sections 34-54 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Rough Working Notes, Sections 55-67 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Rough Working Notes, Sections 68-98 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Handwritten Manuscript, Sections 1-27 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Handwritten Manuscript, Sections 28-73 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Handwritten Manuscript, Sections 75-98 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Endnote Sources, Chapters 1-10 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Endnote Sources, Chapters 11-25 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Endnote Sources, Chapters 26-38 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Endnote Sources, Chapters 39-54 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Endnote Sources, Chapters 55-69 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Endnote Sources, Chapters 70-82 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Endnote Sources, Chapters 83-91 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Endnote Soucres, Chapters 92-97 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Footnotes (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 1 of 9 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 2 of 9 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 3 of 9 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 4 of 9 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 5 of 9 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 6 of 9 (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 7 of 9 (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 8 of 9 (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Trial Transcript Photocopy, Folder 9 of 9 (Box 6, Folder 54)
- Series IV: Photocopies from the Rice University Archives, NYC Archives
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 1 of 19 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 2 of 19 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 3 of 19 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 4 of 19 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 5 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 6 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 7 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 8 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 9 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 10 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 11 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 12 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 13 of 19 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 14 of 19 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 15 of 19 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 16 of 19 (Box 8, Folder 70)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 17 of 19 (Box 8, Folder 71)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 18 of 19 (Box 8, Folder 72)
  - Photocopies of materials from Rice University Archives, Folder 19 of 19 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - Various subject files, Folder 1 of 6 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Various subject files, Folder 2 of 6 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Various subject files, Folder 3 of 6 (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Various subject files, Folder 4 of 6 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - Various subject files, Folder 5 of 6 (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Various subject files, Folder 6 of 6 (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Photocopies of materials from New York City Archives, Folder 1 of 4 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Photocopies of materials from New York City Archives, Folder 2 of 4 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Photocopies of materials from New York City Archives, Folder 3 of 4 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Photocopies of materials from New York City Archives, Folder 4 of 4 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Patrick/ Rice Chronology, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - Patrick/ Rice Chronology, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 85)
  - M.L. Friedland Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - Chronological dates, 1900-1913 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - Lecture Notes, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 88)
  - Early Notes, 1987, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 89)
  - Biographical materials, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 90)
  - Biographical materials, Folder of 2 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Biographies (A to Z), Folder 1 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Biographies (A to Z), Folder 1 of 2 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - Hill Papers photocopies (Syracuse, Albany, NYC) (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - Hill Papers, Folder 1 of 3 (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - Hill Papers, Folder 2 of 3 (Box 11, Folder 96)
  - Hill Papers, Folder 3 of 3 (Box 11, Folder 97)
  - Microfiche and Microfilm from the Hill Papers, Albany, NY (Box 11, Folder -)